with 2024 uh release Wave 2 you can now
integrate U business Central's service
management module with uh field
service I'm Ian and I'm a product
manager in business Central uh product
group and please join me in this couple
of minutes to take you through this new
and exciting capability so integrating
business Central with Dynamics 365 field
service is of particular value to
companies that do regular maintenance or
or they do repairs of the products that
they sell it offers uh managing of the
service task uh handling consumption and
uh aligning Financial transactions that
benefit service technicians that benefit
uh service manager at at the end they
that benefit Finance teams uh on top of
that uh the technicians and dispatchers
can utilize the capability of checking
the inventory
availability at a specific uh Warehouse
or at technician's desk in field service
Based on data that comes in from their
inventory management solution which is
usually business Central this of course
helps optimize work order scheduling
avoids unnecessarily traveling costs or
and helps optimize uh their service and
purchasing operations so we'll start off
by talking about how do we set up uh
integration between field service and uh
service management I have one note to uh
to share with you in here this is a
feature that is becoming available in a
first update or a November update of
2024 release wave one so do keep that in
mind and the setup itself is uh just an
extension of a of an existing
integration that we have between field
service and the projects module that we
have shipped in uh 24 Wave 1 if you want
to check details about that uh make sure
to check the description of the video
and there's a link uh to the video that
we did in a previous release wave for
that integration so let's see this uh in
action so before we dive into a setup I
want to talk a bit about the
prerequisites for enabling uh the
integration to service management module
as you know service management module is
a part of the premium experience so the
first thing that you will need to do in
order even to light up the capabilities
of integrating field service with a
service management module you will need
to turn on a uh premium experience in
your company
information so I've already done that so
just want to point where this is so I've
changed the company experience to
premium another thing that um uh we we
need to do is you need to also ensure uh
that um there's a connection to data
verse there's connection to sales before
you can uh enable um field service
integration but this is all again
explained in the in the video that we've
uh released in the in the previous
release wave and the way to uh to start
a setup is either by uh running it from
a uh assisted setup guide that we have
prepared for this and you can see
there's a new setting that's called
integration type that basically allows
you to set up integration either to
projects or to Service uh management
module or to both and on the next screen
uh what you will see is there's a toggle
uh that actually enables the uh
inventory availability by location in
order to do that you will also need to
have the virtual tables uh enabled of
course the same is uh the same is also
available in uh field service um
integration setup page where you have
these two toggles of uh in the field
service uh picking the integration type
and optionally you can enable inventory
availability once the connection gets
enabled it also deploys the field
service integration solution to field
service and it sets up uh some
additional uh integration table mappings
so if you if you search for the
integration table mappings that start
with FS you will find there's a location
integration table mapping that was added
these were added in the previous release
wave and the project task and if you
scroll down a bit you will find service
order service item line and service
order type integration table mappings uh
that uh have been added after you enable
uh the integration so this is just a
recap of the things that you saw in the
demo we went through the prerequisites
I've talked briefly about U uh
integration uh type and how you can uh
how you can select it there's a couple
of things that happen also after uh the
after the integration gets
enabled um there are some settings in
the service management setup uh that
sort of become locked uh Since U field
service can work with u uh multiple
customer assets we need to disable the
one service line per uh order in the
service management setup we also make
the service order type mandatory because
this is also a mandatory thing on the on
the field service side also we turn on
the archiving of the service uh orders
uh together with uh making sure that the
service order numbering now gets a
manual flag because the the numbering in
field service and in uh service
management uh the numbering of the work
orders or service orders does not need
to be uh the same so that uh so to
ensure the seamless integration the
service order the numbering series needs
to be uh enabled and there's also um for
the when you enable uh inventory
availability one of the things
uh that is sort of a mandatory setup
location mandatory needs to also be uh
turned on and again here is the list of
the uh new integration table mappings
that get added uh uh during uh enabling
of the Integrations this is for for
reference
only okay so now that we have setup done
and we've enabled inventory availability
we've enabled integration of service
management module to uh to field service
uh let's talk about uh inventory
availability and what it actually brings
uh through uh through this uh
integration so let's see that in action
back in business Central after you've
enabled the field service Integrations
you now have uh locations synchronized
with your rare houses right you can
actually go ahead and open uh some of
the items and I'll search for whole
roasted
beans and if I check the whole roasted
beans this is uh one of the items that
uh we have synchronized with uh with
field service and if I look at uh
availability by
location what you will see in here is in
the East Warehouse I have one and in the
main Warehouse I have uh two pieces or
was it kilograms of uh two pieces of uh
whole roasted beans of course if I go
and open a product in field service that
is related that has been synchronized
with uh with this item that we've just
looked at in um in business Central we
will actually be able also to see the
inventory availability so if I go and
click uh items availability by location
you can see the same numbers uh in here
and this is something that gets
particularly useful when you are a
dispatcher trying to schedule uh work
orders or if you're a technician just
trying to figure out how many of
particular items you might have on truck
in your truck or with
you so as a recap of the demo uh what
you saw in this inventory availability
in field service is there's a
prerequisite you need to do this
location to Warehouse map
synchronization this is a unidirectional
synchronization meaning the business
Central given that it's a system of
record for inventory is actually pushing
the location information to uh field
service so we are not picking up any of
this information information uh from
field service when we are sending
location information we exclude the in
transit locations and those that uh that
have Warehouse pick uh mandatory to
support uh the the whole inventory
availability story in here we have added
a uh new API that once you enable the
feature it actually gets uh published as
a virtual table in in field service and
on top of that a synthetic relation uh
between
between the products that we synced and
this uh new virtual table gets created
and that gets you uh this nice view of
uh available inventory in field service
next up is actually I would say a core
of the um field service uh to service
management integration and that's the
service order and work order uh
alignment let's see that in action first
and then we'll talk a bit more about
this feature back in business Central as
I said the topic of uh of this demo is
actually to showcase the service order
and the work order alignment right so
we'll open service orders and you can
see there's a list of service orders uh
there's an information about which ones
of these have been uh already
synchronized with work orders there's a
background task that actually goes and
checks for new service orders and
automatically synchronizes them so this
mapping is set to synchronize basically
everything so we are not we don't have
that synchron coupled records flagged
turned on so the moment you actually
create a service order it is going to
get it is going to start synchronizing
in there and in here I have a service
order for ad incorporation with uh S100
semi-automatic coffee maker for which uh
we are performing let's call it a
regular maintenance and bringing in some
additional coffee beans uh to the
customer we've set up some service we've
uh actually added two items items that
we are bringing as a part of this
maintenance contract that we that we
have now let's see how that actually
looks like in field service and as you
can see the the service order also has
this standard set of actions for for
synchronizing so you can synchronize get
data here and there you can open a
already coupled recorder so let's do
that in here and uh when you land in uh
field service what you can see there's a
data from from the header of the
recorder being transferred such as uh
service account work quot types U
there's information about a uh service
item it's called a primary asset these
uh service items are synchronized to uh
what is called work order incidents so
you can have multiple work order
incidents on the work order as you could
as you would have multiple service item
lines in in service order and when you
look at the products and services you
can actually see those uh products that
we've added in the service order in in
business Central one thing to note as
well is that there is a way of U it's
not only that you need to create a
service order in business Central and
then you send it to uh to field service
there are cases I mean you can receive a
call from a customer a case is going to
be created converted to a uh work order
incident or work order and you can also
synchronize uh work orders the other way
around right
so as I said we have the products we
have the estimated quantities that we've
entered in the in the service order and
what you can see is we also have
Services uh synchronized in there so the
uh dispatcher what is going to have a
look and where this uh inventory
availability feature is going to be uh
super uh interesting is it's going to
check if everything is ready if all the
products actually are there in order for
him to be able to uh schedule this
particular work order let's assume that
this is the case in here and I will just
go ahead and quickly uh schedule this
work
order so I just need location
agnostic and let's just remove these
filters to show available
resources and I will assign this one to
myself and now that the recorder has
been scheduled it's going to get a uh
scheduled status and I'm basically as a
technician when I look at the scheduled
work orders I can just uh pick them on
in uh in order in which uh they arrive
so that's the first part of the story of
the field service and the work order
alignment let's get back to the slides
to uh show you a bit more details all
right so in in in this demo what we saw
was uh service order and work order uh
alignment you as it I said uh there's a
b directional synchronization of of
those things so means that service
orders can come either as a result of
service contracts and and service orders
that created uh related to Service uh
contracts in business Central or they
can come from uh various uh places in in
field service either from opportunity or
a case uh or any other uh way um on the
work order when the work orders actually
come from field service and that get
synchronized in um in business Central
there's actually a new FL that is called
integrate to service which you need to
uh check mark in order to for to
consider that work order in field
service uh to be synchronized back in
the in business
Central as I said service item lines are
aligned with the workorder incidents and
you can have uh one or multiple uh um
customer assets assign associated with
the workorder incidents meaning you can
have uh one or more service item lines
on the on the service order and of
course as I said uh service lines on the
other hand get the line to worker
product and worker Service uh data where
you have the the estimated quantities
and duration uh synchronized uh to
indicate uh to the dispatcher that this
is something to uh look at and the
important thing to note is that
estimated quantities and the quantity
field actually just gets synchronized to
work order up until the work order
reaches the scheduled status that's when
we stop
synchronizing uh quantity from the uh
from the service lines but we continue
synchronizing uh quantity to ship
quantity to consum and quantity to
invoice as you will see in the in the
next uh
demo so the next part of uh our uh
presentation today is how do you handle
uh consumption and invoicing of the work
orders that get uh scheduled that get
executed and then need to be invoiced uh
to a customer let's see that in a demo
first all right so as a technician
actually goes and works through the work
orders that have been scheduled once he
Arise at the location he will set the uh
booking status to in progress and now as
he starts executing on the work order of
course one of the things that's going to
be uh also done is going to to utilize
the materials or the parts that he has
brought with him to uh to execute the
work order and let's say that uh when he
came to the customer he actually saw
that there's enough of the copy beans
that he doesn't need to but he just uh
needs uh he just used uh one in here so
back in business Central uh the
dispatcher or the back office is going
to also see the status of the order
reflected in business
Central and they can basically track uh
what is happening with that order by
automatically synchronizing or manually
just getting data from data verse and uh
they can repeat this process as many
times as they wish up until the
workorder sort of reaches the status uh
completed in U in field service as they
synchronize the data they will see the
updates to uh quantity to ship and
quantity to consume reflected in
business
Central now if we switch back to uh work
order in field service so the technician
has used the uh the products and the
materials he has completed his service
in there and what he's going to do is he
will set the status completed to the
work order in field
service so once the work order is
completed in field service from the
standpoint of the integration it is
considered ready to be posted in uh in
business Central back in business
Central what you can again see is the
status gets uh reflected when the
recorder is set to complet it it gets
set to the status finished in here and
that's an indication for the back office
uh Personnel to go ahead and uh start
posting the order they will see the
latest uh information about the
consumption of services consumption of
materials
and once they are happy with this they
will go ahead and simply ship and
consume because there is some things
that need to be consumed
first and we will also do ship an
invoice for this uh
order for the remaining
bits now once the service invoice uh
gets posted and U and the service order
gets uh closed this is again going to be
reflected back in field service where
the field service where in the field
service the work order basically
receives the status posted so looking
back in field service what you can see
is that uh this work order is now in the
State uh posted meaning that the the
processing and the invoicing of the work
order has been completed and that wraps
up uh this part of the demo so as a
recap of the last demo uh what we saw
was the service line alignment with uh
uh workor
with work order we say that there is a b
directional synchronization of that but
you need to take that into account that
it is sort of a conditional B
directional synchronization so what you
saw that we had use quantities and
durations uh getting aligned uh up until
the work order is in completed status
and even in the completed status it can
be done but then you know there needs to
be some conversation between the
technician and the back office work to
say okay well you know now we are done
uh we are done updating the
uh the the work order all of the partial
postings that you might have done
um up until the moment that the the work
order got to that completed status will
be automatically aligned through
quantity shipped and quantity consumed
fields in uh um in field service and uh
as I said the completed work order means
ready to uh to be posted and once this
is uh once this is all done the
workorder status gets uh posted status
and then it gets actually locked for any
uh further editing and of course the
resources and the durations that you've
consumed through the booking are also uh
transferred back to uh to to service
order as something that uh you will only
consume in business Central because the
service uh the service uh the service
line item is the one that gets invoiced
uh to the customer it's similar to to
what we have done uh with uh um field
service to projects
integration and that was it and I really
hope you enjoy this video do keep in
mind that uh this feature is going to
get going to become available with
update one of 2024 release wave uh 2
meaning November uh update in the
meantime uh please check down the
description below for the uh links to
the previous releasee wave videos and
the field service integration to uh
projects and have a look at uh other
useful links uh that we've provided in
the description of the video below thank
you for your time